Guide to the Vladimir Samarin (Sokolov) Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Vladimir Samarin correspondence and other papers
1948-1976
GEN MSS 295
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
Incoming (86 TLS, 85 ALS) and carbons of outgoing (127 TL) correspondence, mostly regarding Russian émigré publications, literary and church affairs. Includes the typescript of Samarin's "Front v tylu (Bolʹshevistskoe podpolʹe v zani︠a︡tykh nemt︠s︡ami oblasti︠a︡kh SSSR, 98 p., 1951) and the page-proofs of works by Ivan Alekseevich Bunin with annotations by Bunin.
Samarin, Vladimir D., pseud.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase and gift from V. D. Samarin (Sokolov).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
VLADIMIR SAMARIN (SOKOLOV)
Vladimir Samarin was born Vladimir Dmitrievich Sokolov March 2, 1913 in the central Russian city of Orel. In 1936, despite some troubles encountered due to his family's bourgeois background, he completed the local Institute and commenced a career teaching Russian literature in Voronezh.
Under German occupation in 1942-1944 Samarin wrote for the newspapers Rech (based in Orel) and Volia naroda. Upon arriving at a camp for displaced persons (DPs) in post-war Germany he continued his journalistic calling in new émigré publications. In addition to contributing anti-communist commentaries and short-stories to various journals, he was editor of Put' (1946-1949) and Posev (1949-1951) and a prominent member of the anti-communist Natsional'no-trudovoi soiuz (NTS). In 1951, Samarin emigrated to the United States, where he worked for a while as a copy-editor for the Chekhov Publishing House in New York. He continued to write for émigré journals such as Grani and Vozrozhdenie, and for the newspapers Novoe russkoe slovo and La pensée russe. In 1964, Samarin published his first collection of stories, Peschanaia otmel', which was followed by TSvet vremeni (1969), Teni na stene (1972) and Teplyi mramor (1976). In 1972, Samarin collected his travel sketches into the book Dalekaia zvezda. That same year, he published in English an impassioned account of the Russian Orthodox Church under Soviet rule, Triumphant Cain. An Outline of the Calvary of the Russian Church.
Samarin was a lecturer of Russian language at Yale University from 1959. In 1976, the Soviet propaganda organ "Sowjetisches Heimland" called attention to his wartime activities as a collaborationist journalist. He subsequently resigned his position at Yale and was deported to Canada, where he died on January 19, 1992. Samarin is buried at Novo-Diveevo cemetary in Spring Valley, New York.
Scope and Contents
Series I: Correspondence includes letters to Samarin from Russian émigré literateurs and church figures and a significant quantity of his replies. Of particular note are letters from G. V. Adamovich, G. V. Ivanov, A. F. Kerensky, Archimandrite Konstantin (Zaitsev), N. O. Losskii, Nikolai Vladimirovich Narokov, Aleksandra L'vovna Tolstaia and B. K. Zaitsev. The main topics of discussion are political developments in the USSR, major events in émigré literary life and the worsening schism between the Russian Orthodox Church outside Russia and what became the Orthodox Church in America. Series II: Other Papers, includes a long essay and an obituary by Samarin, and also corrected proofs by I. A. Bunin, apparently preserved from Samarin's days at the Chekhov Publishing House.
Novoe russkoe slovo; Pravoslavnai︠a︡ Rusʹ; Russkai︠a︡ myslʹ (Paris, France: 1947); Russia -- Emigration and immigration; Anastasīĭ, Metropolitan, 1873-1965; Konstantin, Archimandrite; Adamovich, Georgiĭ, 1892-1972; Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1886-1957; Belinkov, A. (Arkadiĭ), 1921-1970; Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1870-1953; Gazdanov, Gaito, 1903-1971; Ivanov, Georgiĭ, 1894-1958; Kerensky, Aleksandr Fyodorovich, 1881-1970; Losskiĭ, N. O. (Nikolaĭ Onufrievich), 1870-1965; Nicolaevsky, Boris I., 1887-1966; Samarin, Vladimir; Sikorsky, Igor Ivan, 1889-1972; Sokolova, Tatʹi︠a︡na Georgievna; Tolstoy, Alexandra, 1884-1979; Veĭnbaum, M. E. (Mark Efimovich), 1890-1973; Zaĭt︠s︡ev, Boris, 1881-1972; Zenzinov, V. (Vladimir), 1880-1953; Zurov, Leonid, 1902-1971; Izdatelʹstvo imeni Chekhova (New York, N.Y.); Narodno-trudovoĭ soi︠u︡z; Russkai͡a pravoslavnai͡a t͡serkovʹ zagranit͡seĭ; Tolstoy Foundation (U.S.)
- Correspondence, Series I
  - LETTERS RECEIVED
    - Adamovich, Georgii Viktorovich, 1965-72 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1954 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Pseudonym of M. A. Landau
    - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1955-58 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Andreevskii, B., 1959-63 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Argus, Mikhail Konstantinovich, 1965-70 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Pseudonym of M. K. Aizenshtadt
    - Belinkov, Arkadii, 1969 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dalin, D., 1951 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Domogatskii, Boris, 1965-67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gazdanov, Gaito, 1971 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Grinberg, Roman Nikolaevich, 1965-68 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ivanov, Georgii Vladimirovich, 1952 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Kerensky, Alexander, 1954-67 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Konstantin (Zaitsev), Archimandrite, 1967-71 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Kravchenko, Viktor, 1951 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lebedev, Fedor Tarasovich, 1957-63 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes TSentral'noe politicheskoe ob"edinenie politicheskikh emigrantov
    - Losskii, Nikolai Onufrievich, 1958 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Maksimov, Sergei Sergeevich, 1949-55 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Pseudonym of S. S. Pashin
    - Margolin,IUlii, 1970 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mozhaiskaia, Ol'ga Nikolaevna, 1970-73 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Narokov, Nikolai Vladimirovich, 1949-69 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Neledinskii, E. N., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Nikolaevskii, Boris, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Also spelled Nicolaevsky
    - Ol'shanskii, B., 1953-54 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Possev-Verlag, 1962 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes A. Svetlanin
    - Nikon (Rklitskii), Archbishop, 1975 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Savin, Valerian Luk'ianovich, 1964-66 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes Sovremennik
    - Sikorsky, Igor Ivanovich, 1957-58 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Solonevich, Ivan Luk'ianovich, 1948-53 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Tolstaia, Aleksandra L'vovna, 1962-76 (Box 1, Folder 30-34)
    - Ugriumov, Aleksei Ivanovich, 1964-68 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Pseudonym of A. I. Pliushkov
    - Vodov, Sergei Akimovich, 1964-66, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Includes La pensée russe
    - Weinbaum, Mark, 1971 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Includes Novoe russkoe slovo
    - Zaitsev, Boris Konstantinovich, 1956-72 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Zenzinov, Vladimir Mikhailovich, 1949 Jan 24 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Zurov, Leonid Fedorovich, 1968-71 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - LETTERS SENT
    - Adamovich, Georgii Viktorovich, 1965-72 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1955 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Argus, Mikhail Konstantinovich, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Belinkov, Arkadii, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Ivanov, Georgii Vladimirovich, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Kerenskii, Aleksandr Fedorovich, 1959-63 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Lebedev, Fedor Tarasovich, 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Losskii, Nikolai Onufrievich, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Maksimov, Sergei Sergeevich, 1955 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Mozhaiskaia, Ol'ga Nikolaevna, 1973 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Narokov, Nikolai Vladimirovich, 1954-69 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Savin, Valerian Luk'ianovich, 1964-69 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Sikorsky, Igor' Ivanovich, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Ugriumov, Aleksei Ivanovich, 1964 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Vodov, Sergei Akimovich, 1960-64 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Weinbaum, Mark, 1964-72 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      Includes Novoe russkoe slovo and Literaturnyi fond
    - Zaitsev, Boris Konstantinovich, 1956-72 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Zurov, Leonid Fedorovich, 1968-71 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Other Papers, Series II
  - BUNIN, IVAN ALEKSEEVICH
    - Mitina liubov'. Solnechnyi udar: proof pages, corrected, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Vesnoi v Iudee: proof pages, holograph additions, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - SOKOLOV-SAMARIN, VLADIMIR DMITRIEVICH
    - "Front v tylu (Bol'shevistskoe podpol'e v zaniatykh nemtsami oblastiakh SSSR)": typescript, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Untitled speech on Nikolai Vladimirovich Narokov: typescript, 1969 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 62)